<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>permanent futures</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 19:34:06 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 19:34:06 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dangerous Books</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;dangerous-books-is-a-small-space-with-a-high-ceiling&quot;&gt;Dangerous Books is a small space with a high ceiling.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aisles are narrow and labyrinthine. The shelves are tall; so tall you need a footstool to reach the higher books. Footstools are always easy to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The store only stocks high-quality books, no chaff. The books are not organized by genre, but if you were to accomplish a Fourier transform, re-sorting them into the dusty ghettos of an abandoned Borders, you would find much Science Fiction and very little Romance. Many volumes of Cultural Studies, but few of Business &amp;amp; Management. Heaps of Science &amp;amp; Nature. One Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The back of the store hosts a small reading room, with comfortable chairs and a large, low table. It is said that meetings are held here, but it is not said what sort of Clubbs might find their home at Dangerous Books. There is no sign on the sidewalk advertising events. There is no bulletin board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The front of the shop is brighter. Daylight streams in through tall windows. Here there is a counter: an altar to Hermes, god of messengers and tricksters and thieves. An assortment of particularly dangerous books grace the window display. A small bar in one corner offers hot beverages but few seats; should you desire to get comfortable, you must find your way through the maze to the reading room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking center stage is a massive globe, demarcated not by national boundary but by bioregion. The mountains and oceans and great rivers of the world are hand-painted and filigreed. The moon orbits on a hidden engine, sized to scale but unnaturally close. On the walls are framed maps of imaginary territories: Middle-Earth, Arrakis, Earthsea. Like an old Explorer’s Clubb, veterans of epic campaigns reminisce teary-eyed at the sight of the long-lost lands where they gained and lost so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Announced in a fine script above the altar of Hermes is a challenge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Welcome to Dangerous Books. All books here are known to be Puissant, Arcane, or Memetically Active. They should be used under occult supervision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Books in the Restricted Section are available for purchase, but first you must unveil the Restricted Section. If you need assistance, please do not ask us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beneath, in hasty block letters, another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“PLEASE DO NOT FEED THE BOOKS!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever anyone enters the front door, a small gong peals from a hidden chamber. It pierces at first, but then melts away into the musty, incense-filled atmosphere. It fades so gradually that you cannot be certain whether it has stopped ringing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2018 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/dangerous-books</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/dangerous-books</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Social Systems</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-used-to-live-at-a-wilderness-commune&quot;&gt;I used to live at a wilderness commune.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For three years I woke up every day surrounded by trees and streams and the gossip of songbirds. It was idyllic in many ways, and exactly the sort of thing recommended by “digital detox” clickbait articles. I checked my phone about once a month, when we drove the 60 miles to town for supplies. We had one computer with internet, and it was an old satellite connection, useful for email but nothing else. We had a library of musty books, a copy of Wikipedia on a DVD, and a drawerful of abandoned diaries. That was the totality of our entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that we had each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not getting all mushy here – we didn’t necessarily &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; each other. We just had a community, which meant we could be infinitely entertained. Social experimentation was built into the DNA of the place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was founded by hippies escaping SF in the 70’s, meant to be a protected space for prototyping the communist society of the future. That failed, of course. Most of the hippies moved on. The commune is in a land trust, though, and the founders designed it to be unstoppable. They programmed it in legal code, building incentives and defining limits to behavior. They gave it a runtime of sixty years, turned it on, and one by one they walked away. Most grew neckties, named their babies Dylan, and fulfilled the destiny of the Me Generation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inbuilt rules were like most codebases: kludgy. Simple communal axioms, like &lt;em&gt;“everyone should share”&lt;/em&gt;, get encrusted with real-world precedents like “except for guns, guns should belong to the people who can be trusted with them”, which then breeds with &lt;em&gt;“no one should ever use violence”&lt;/em&gt; to create “the only people who should be allowed to own guns are people who either A) claim to be complete pacifists or B) find it more important to own a gun than to follow the rules.” How do you enforce that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or what about when &lt;em&gt;“love all people”&lt;/em&gt; was applied to &lt;em&gt;“everyone should share”&lt;/em&gt; and we ended up with &lt;em&gt;“it’s time to have a conversation about scabies”?&lt;/em&gt; (Don’t look it up. It’s curable. That’s all you need to know.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But compared to 21C police-state America, the rules were flexible, and a new crop of open-minded hipster throwbacks would show up every year ready to reinvent civilization all over again. So we had a lot of social experimentation. It was like a fucking reality show with no audience. Like maybe the squirrels were watching us or something, and probably the FBI, and the occasional wide-eyed yuppie on a “tech detox”. But that was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did it on purpose. A hodgepodge of idealists with different ideals, all competing to lay our magic on the others, to have our narratives played out on the Stage of Nobody Watching. One small farm to fight for, unending messiahs and vigilantes. We tried a lot of different things. I lasted longer than most, saw more iterations of the game, but I left. No one I know is still there, but it’s still happening. It’s a platform for communisms. It’s a prototyping printer for social dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I learned anything there, it’s that people will play to the rules of any game. We’re malleable. We’re adaptable. We’ll try to succeed, in whatever way the culture defines it. We’ll take the route from where we are to what we think we want, no matter how circuitous or baffling it seems. We’re improv masters, seamlessly slipping between personalities as we move from scene to scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the rules we play by matter. They’re only supported by collective momentum, by a sort of fervent dreaming of the group, but they matter. Whether you stand in a breadline or a checkout lane,  whether you know your neighbors or your family, work to support others or to support yourself: these decisions have consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking about this in the context of Joe Edelman’s letter to Zuck last week. He talks about how the tech monopolies are ultimately responsible for how their platforms are used, and what they could do about it. And he’s right. This is the same magic that the hippies did in the forest: you open 
a space where a new kind of interaction can be played out, and you tune the underlying system to produce a certain outcome. The reason Fakbok seems to be full of shrill brittle people reacting to twisted clickbait so-called “news”, instead of a place to celebrate your connections and shared values: it optimizes for addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doesn’t social media feel a little tweeky these days? Spun? Like a party with the bad drugs: everybody’s talking over each other, normal social taboos are off the table, people are buying and selling things, a bunch of hucksters from Red Bull in the corner pretending they’re not hucksters from Red Bull, bad music videos and memes all over the place, arguments that can immediately turn into screaming gangfights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a trap house. They’re slinging dopamine in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m hopeful that other tools for communication will be designed with better mentalities. Secure Scuttlebutt is a friend-of-a-friend messaging system, which seems to be in line with a more human-scale approach to socialization. It’s still in its early stages, but the developers are also the users, so the conversations about how it will grow are happening &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;, in the platform. Other new models for digital socialism are on the way, in the blockchain and meshnet and the rest. We need to be vigilant, to critique the assumptions of the systems we’re using. Edelman’s other article TK TK TK
gives a decent set of criteria for social relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s up to us. The power of any network is the product of the square of its nodes. The platform with the most users gets the most power. So where would you rather meet me – in the world’s biggest trap house, or in a little Ewok village in the woods?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/social-systems</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/social-systems</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Magic Isn't Real</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;##I like to talk about “cognitive security” in these virtual pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cogsec. It’s a word I found lying around on the internet. It’s mildly stained with connotation. The (ugh) cybernihilists were on it last year, but seem to have wandered off and left it relatively unmolested. IBM is trying to make it an industry buzzword associated with their brand so they can appear to be on the cutting edge of something for once. But for the most part it was sitting there like a free kitten or a couch on the curb, full of potential sorely neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I took it. It’s a simple idea if you don’t dance circles around it like the academics (or the cybernihilist CHUDs):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cognitive security is the study of influence for influence’s sake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s related to these nifty new tech things, so it got this nifty techno-techno name, but it’s not new. It’s as old as the human mind. To claim a “continual arms race to influence — and protect from influence — large groups of users online” is only to describe a new battlefront in an ancient war.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Influencing large groups of people – online or off – is the business of empires, religions, corporations. It’s the business of business. It’s the entire basis of politics. Since the beginning of language, we’ve been able to project our thoughts into nearby minds, and we’ve already developed a wide range of techniques and technologies for influencing large groups of users. There’s a lot of apps on that platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that we have more data now than ever in history. We have more science, more knowledge of the limits of human cognition. We have titanic databases of “personal data” – that is, the surveillance files collected on you by the spyware merchants at Fazbok and Gugel. On second thought, “we” don’t have that, do we? They do. Funny, that. Somebody should really start some kind of data co-op or something. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, the revolution in communication is one of scale, not one of quality. The same techniques that have been developed for ten thousand years are being carried over into the automated world. Meet the new gods, same as the old gods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it’s magic, right? Social engineering, cognitive security, applied memetics: all of these buzzwords point to the same realm of ideas, but dare not speak its true name. Magic. Magic is not new, but now we can do it through computers. It’s worth looking at, which is why I started this cogsec newsletter. We have to protect ourselves from novel threats, and the cybernihilists, obviously, don’t give a shit. Somebody had to pick up the thread. What kinds of magic are we facing in the 21C, and what tools do we have to defend ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, don’t get me wrong: magic isn’t real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not. I know some of you might take this kind of hard, so I hope you’re sitting down. Take a drink of water or something. Harry Potter was a lie. Sorry. You’re not going to get a letter by owl, you’re not going to find the secret teachings on the internet, you’re not going to find a book of power at the library on a shelf no one ever saw before. Magic isn’t real. It’s okay – once you say it to yourself, it doesn’t hurt anymore. You were already living in a world where magic isn’t real, knowing about it doesn’t make it worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that magic isn’t useful. Like I said, it’s a 10,000-year-old technology and it’s ubiquitous in society. It’s not just not real, it’s just not real yet. It’s the art of seeing possible things, counterfactual worlds, and influencing the reality around you to make them come true. Magic is making things happen. It’s the “Art and Science of causing Change in conformity with Will,” as Aleister Crowley put it, and the man was considered a famous wizard during his own lifetime. He made that happen. He was gross, but he was a magician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The huckster who sells you a busted car off Craglits is also a magician. He exploits your cognitive biases to influence your behavior. So does the priest in the pulpit, the drill sergeant, the slicked-back skinny-tie ad man. Oh, sorry, they’re called “creative strategists” now, not “ad men”. And they wear hoodies. Anyway, they’re all dark wizards and they hate you and want you to do things you would never do, so they use magic to make you want things you don’t want. They know what they’re doing, although they probably have a nice rationalization that lets them sleep at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magic is everywhere, and it’s explicit. There’s a well-circulated document that shows how Pepsi’s “Smile” logo was created – you can probably google “Pepsi Arnell” and find it. This Arnell character made a 27-page proposal showing how the Golden Ratio was the secret to creating a logo that would transform into a hypersphere and engulf the Consumer in a Pepsi Universe. No kidding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PICTURE TK TK&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One million dollars they paid him for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when the document was leaked a lot of “creative strategists” called it a total fraud. Even the creator said it was bullshit. Well, actually, what he said was “It’s all bullshit… A logo on a can of soda? Please. My life is bullshit.”&lt;strong&gt;LINK TK TK&lt;/strong&gt; Which is probably also true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it worked. Pepsi’s had that logo for ten years now. It cost them over a billion dollars to replace all their packaging, so it must have been successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Did the folder full of steaming hype delude the minds of the C-suite at PepsiCo for a solid decade? Did the logo design actually meet some deep human need for golden proportions and dynamic forces? Or does the smiling globe actually “The Gravitational Force of Pepsi”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn’t matter. The magic worked. Lines on paper and magic chanting made something happen in the real world. Just because the shaman was wearing a necktie and standing in a boardroom, doesn’t mean it wasn’t magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So magic isn’t real, but that doesn’t matter, because it still works. To study cogsec is to study magic in the 21st century. Defense against the dark arts. Consider this letter Sent By Owl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Max&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/posts/magic-isn't-real</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/posts/magic-isn't-real</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
